A Finding Aid to the Solon H. Borglum and Borglum Family Papers, 1864-2002, in the Archives of American Art AAA.borgsolo
Archives of American Art
Solon H. Borglum and Borglum family papers
1864-2002
AAA.borgsolo
Archives of American Art
11.4 Linear feet
The Solon H. Borglum and Borglum family papers date from 1864 to 2002 and measure 11.4 linear feet. The collection documents Solon Borglum's personal life and his career as a sculptor specializing in Western themes through biographical material, family and general correspondence, writings and notes, research for his biography, financial and business letters, printed material, photographs and artwork.
Borglum, Solon Hannibal
Biographical Note
Solon Hannibal Borglum was born in Ogden, Utah in 1868. His father Jens (James) Borglum and wife Ida emigrated to America in 1864, as Mormon converts. James took a second wife Christina who was the mother of Solon and his older brother John Gutzon de la Mothe. Christina left the family after just a few years, when James left the Mormon Church. James and Ida raised the large family, which included Solon, Gutzon, Miller, Arnold, August, Anna, Harriet, Theodora and Frank. Solon spent most of his childhood in Fremont, Nebraska, and in 1893 he became a ranch hand in Southern California. At this time he also developed an interest in art which he shared with his brother Gutzon, who was studying painting in Los Angeles.
From 1885 to 1893 Solon ran a ranch on his father's land in central Nebraska, but also took painting lessons from artist J. Laurie Wallace. After spending a short time at his brother's studio in Sierra Madre, and living as an artist in Santa Ana, he studied at the Cincinnati Art Academy under Louis T. Rebisso from 1895 to 1897. Solon then went to Paris where he met sculptor Augustus Saint-Gaudens who persuaded him to study sculpture at the Academie Julian. He studied there under Denys Puech and won numerous awards for works exhibited both in France and the United States. In 1898 Solon married Emma Vignal in Paris. They spent four months at the Crow Creek Reservation in South Dakota, an experience that greatly influenced his work. In 1901 Solon was elected to the National Sculpture Society, later becoming its vice president, and set up a studio in New York. Despite his success, such as winning the gold medal at the Art Palace at the 1904 World's Fair, confusions began between him and his brother Gutzon who decided to also become a sculptor. In 1906 he moved with his wife and children, Paul and Monica, to a farm in Connecticut called "Rocky Ranch." Artist Paul Manship became his student helper and lived with the family. Solon received commissions to do many monuments and memorials, but also continued to exhibit his work and participate in the local Silvermine Group of Artists.
From 1916 to 1917 Solon taught at the Beaux-Arts Institute of Design in New York and also developed ideas for an art textbook called Sound Construction, which he worked on with his student assistant Mildred Archer Nash. In 1918, he enlisted in the YMCA for overseas war work, attached to the Third and Fifth French Army. While there he was also the Director of Sculpture at the specially organized American Expeditionary Forces Art Training Center. When he returned home, he decided to establish the School of American Sculpture in New York City. He ran the school with great success, and gave many lectures on art and his experiences overseas until his sudden death after an appendectomy in January of 1922. His legacy was carried on by his wife Emma until her death in 1934, at which point his daughter Monica and her husband, A. Mervyn Davies, oversaw the exhibition of his artwork, and in 1974 published his biography Solon H. Borglum: "A Man Who Stands Alone".
Scope and Contents note
The Solon H. Borglum and Borglum family papers date from 1864 to 2002 and measure 11.4 linear feet. The collection documents Solon Borglum's personal life and his career as a sculptor specializing in Western themes through biographical material, family and general correspondence, writings and notes, research for his biography, financial and business letters, printed material, photographs and artwork.
Biographical material contains documents providing information on the Borglum Family history as well as Solon's military service and memorial. Also found is a leather portfolio of ephemera kept by Emma Borglum. Family correspondence includes numerous letters between Solon and Emma and various members of their extended family. The letters discuss family events, everyday life, Solon's military service, and family history. General Correspondence pertains to Solon's career as an artist and includes his incoming and outgoing correspondence with galleries, foundries, patrons, fellow artists such as Augustus Saint-Gaudens, and others. Later correspondence from galleries, museums, foundries, historical societies, and other individuals and organizations, is addressed to his daughter Monica Borglum and concerns Solon's artwork and legacy after his death. Writings and notes include material written by Solon Borglum and material written by others. Solon's writings include project proposals as well as essays, lectures, and other notes on the topics of his own works of art, art and form, and his participation in World War I. Also found are Solon's diary, notebooks, and address books kept during the last five years of his life. Writings by others include writings by Emma and others about Solon Borglum, as well as guest books for the Silvermine Group of Artists.
Series five contains documents compiled by Monica Borglum Davies and her husband A. Mervyn Davies for a biography Solon Borglum. Included are their research files and notes as well as heavily edited drafts of book sections and draft manuscripts and notes. Financial and business records document Solon's professional career and legacy, including project contracts and financial proposals, account books, ledgers, receipts, and items regarding the Solon H. Borglum Sculpture and Education Fund. Printed material contains items about Solon Borglum's career and artwork compiled by his daughter, Monica Davies, and includes exhibition catalogs, exhibition announcements, brochures, programs, clippings, reports, and other publications. Also included is the textbook Sound Construction.
This collection also contains numerous photographs, including Solon's personal and family photographs, and photographs of his artwork. Family and personal photographs consist of photos of Solon taken throughout his career, including his time in military service, photos of his family and friends, various studios and residences including Rocky Ranch, and of him and and Emma at the Crow Creek Reservation. Artwork is comprised of sketches Solon made for his sculptural works and for Sound Construction. Also found are sketches by Emma and Gutzon Borglum, including a sketch of Solon, and artwork by others such as artist Robert Fulton Logan.
Arrangement
The collection is arranged into 9 series. Glass plate negatives are housed separately and closed to researchers.
Series 1: Biographical Material, 1866, 1895-1922, undated (Box 1, 13; 10 folders)
Series 2: Family Correspondence, 1885-1972, undated (Box 1; 0.4 linear feet)
Series 3: General Correspondence, 1871-1989, undated (Box 1-2; 1.0 linear foot)
Series 4: Writings and Notes, 1871-1983, undated (Box 2-3; 1.0 linear foot)
Series 5: Solon Borglum Biography, 1870-1975, undated (Box 3-8; 5.3 linear feet)
Series 6: Financial and Business Records, 1898-1998, undated (Box 8, 13; 0.2 linear feet)
Series 7: Printed Material, 1879-2002, undated (Box 9, 13-14; 1.1 linear feet)
Series 8: Photographs, 1864-1986 (Box 9-13, MGP 1, MGP 3, OV 15-16; 2.0 linear feet)
Series 9: Artwork, 1890-1921, undated (Box 12-13; 0.3 linear feet)
Provenance
Most of the materials in the collection were originally loaned by the Borglum family between 1969-1975 and microfilmed. Much of the same material was later donated in several accretions between circa 1991-2004 by various family members David Borglum, Harriet M. Borglum, Alfred Davies, Harold Davies, Monica B. Davies, Linda Borglum Fry, and Gwynneth Kelly. In 1979 approximately 200 photographs were transferred from the Smithsonian American Art Museum Library to AAA, which had received them from Monica Borglum Davies.
Separated Material
A scrapbook of news clippings, other printed material, writings, and correspondence were loaned for microfilming in 1969 by Solon's daughter, Monica Borglum Davies. Originals were returned to Monica Borglum Davies and George Borglum after microfilming. Loaned material is available on reels N69-98 and 1054. Loaned material that was not later donated and merged is not described in this finding aid.
Related Material
The Archives also holds several collections related to the Borglum family, including the Gutzon Borglum collection, available on microfilm only, reel 3056. This collection includes correspondence, printed material, and photographs. Originals reside at the San Antonio Museum of Art. Also found are the Gutzon Borglum letters to John A. Stewart (available on microfilm reel D8, frames 359-362) and the Harriet Collins Allen papers relating to Solon Borglum. The Library of Congress also holds papers of Solon Hannibal Borglum and is the primary repository of the papers of Gutzon Borglum.
Alternative Forms Available
The papers of sculptor Solon Borglum and the Borglum Family were digitized in 2006 by the Archives of American Art, and total 6177 images.
Materials not digitized include a few certificates, writings and notes not authored by Solon but by others, Monica Borglum Davies research files for and drafts of the biography Solon H. Borglum, A Man Who Stands Alone, 1974, some routine financial materials, clippings and magazines, and photographs of artwork. Loaned portions of the collection, most of which was later donated, merged, digitized, are available on 35mm microfilm reels N69-98 and 1054 at Archives of American Art offices and for interlibrary loan.
Restrictions on Access
The bulk of the collection has been digitized and is available online via AAA's website. Use of material not digitized requires an appointment. Glass plate negatives are housed separately and closed to researchers.
Borglum, Emma Vignal, 1866-1934; Borglum, Gutzon, 1867-1941; Davies, A. Mervyn (Alfred Mervyn); Davies, Monica Borglum, 1903-; Sculptors--Connecticut--Wilton; Sculpture, American--United States; Sculpture--Study and teaching; Sketches; World War, 1914-1918
- Biographical Material, 1866, 1895-1922, undated; Series 1; (Box 1, 13; 10 folders)
  Scope and Contents note
  Biographical material includes citizenship papers for Solon's father, James Borglum, death certificates for two relatives, and other genealogical documents on the history of the Borglum Family. Also found are photographs, clippings, and other ephemera gathered in a leather portfolio by Emma Borglum. This series also contains items documenting Solon's role as Scoutmaster in Silvermine, as well as his service in World War I. Also found are written tributes and printed material for the Solon Borglum Memorials held at Saint Mark's in-the-Bouwerie and the National Sculpture Society. Folders are arranged chronologically by subject.
  - Declaration of Intention for Citizenship, James Borglum, 1866 (Box 1, Folder 1)
  - Death Certificates for Harry and Dagmar Wilson, 1895-1896 (Box 1, Folder 2)
  - Borglum Family History, 1896, undated (Box 1, Folder 3)
  - Emma Borglum Scrapbook/Porfolio, 1912, undated; (3 folders) (Box 1, Folder 4-6)
  - Silvermine Boy Scout Troop, 1912, 1914 (Box 1, Folder 7)
  - Military Documents for Solon Borglum, 1917-1919; (See also Box 13, F1) (Box 1, Folder 8)
  - Solon Borglum Memorials, 1922 (Box 1, Folder 9)
  - Military Documents for Solon Borglum, 1917-1919; (See also Box 1, F8) (Box 13 (sol), Folder 1)
- Family Correspondence, 1885-1972, undated; Series 2; (Box 1; 0.4 linear feet)
  Family Correspondence includes numerous letters between Solon and his wife Emma and his children, Paul and Monica. Most of their correspondence is from 1918 through 1919 while Solon was in the military in France. There are also many letters to Monica from Emma during the period shortly after Solon's death. Also found are letters to Solon from his parents James and Ida; and letters to Emma from her parents Jean and Lydie Vignal. There are also many letters to Emma from her sister Lucy Vignal Borglum, who married Solon's brother August, and to Emma from her sister-in-law Elizabeth Vignal, who was married to Emma's brother Paul. Also included are numerous letters to Lucy Vignal Borglum from her parents. Most of the correspondence between the Vignals is in French. This series also contains other family correspondence including letters between Solon and his siblings, letters between Solon's brother August and other family members including several cousins, letters between Monica and Paul, Monica and her Aunt Harriet, and her cousin George Borglum, August Borglum's son. Much of this later correspondence discusses family history.
  - To wife Emma (and children) from Solon Borglum, 1907-1911, 1918-1919, undated; (8 folders) (Box 1, Folder 10-17)
  - To Solon from wife Emma, 1901-1910 (Box 1, Folder 18)
  - To Solon from wife Emma and Children, 1914-1919, undated; (3 folders) (Box 1, Folder 19-21)
  - To Solon from parents James and Ida, 1897-1909, undated (Box 1, Folder 22)
  - To Monica Borglum from her mother Emma, 1922-1925, undated; (4 folders) (Box 1, Folder 23-26)
  - To Emma from sister Lucy Vignal Borglum, 1903-1913, undated (Box 1, Folder 27)
  - To Emma from sister-in-law Elizabeth Vignal, 1904-1923, undated (Box 1, Folder 28)
  - To Emma from parents Jean and Lydie Vignal, 1902-1918 (Box 1, Folder 29)
  - To Lucy Vignal Borglum from parents Jean and Lydie Vignal, 1902-1907, undated; (4 folders) (Box 1, Folder 30-33)
  - Family Correspondence, 1885-1972, undated; (5 folders) (Box 1, Folder 34-38)
- General Correspondence, 1871-1989, undated; Series 3; (Box 1-2; 1.0 linear foot)
  This series includes Solon Borglum's incoming and outgoing professional correspondence. Materials dated after 1922 are Monica Borglum Davies' incoming correspondence regarding Solon's artwork and legacy. Solon's correspondence is with galleries and foundries, such as the Milch Gallery and Roman Bronze Works, concerning the sale or production of his artwork, and correspondence with people and organizations, such as Jane Wallace and Saint Mark's in-the-Bouwerie, concerning sculpture projects, and with other artists, including August Saint-Gaudens and Robert Fulton Logan. Also found is correspondence concerning the School of American Sculpture, both before and after Solon's death.
  Materials addressed to Monica Borglum include letters from art galleries and museums, such as the Detroit Institute of Art, the Joslyn Art Museum, and the National Collection of Fine Arts at the Smithsonian Institution, concerning the sale or exhibition of Solon's artwork. Also included is correspondence with foundries concerning the production of Solon's sculptures, and with historical societies, individuals, and other organizations concerning the provenance, collection, or exhibition of his artwork. This series also includes correspondence from the Solon Borglum Memorial Fund and condolences to Monica on the deaths of Solon and Emma (in 1934).
  Also found are calling cards, business cards, and envelopes that have been separated from their contents. This series also includes numerous notepads containing drafts of Solon's outgoing correspondence as well as drafts on loose pages.
  - American Art Foundry, 1925-1928 (Box 1, Folder 39)
  - Collings, Ruth M., 1964-1983 (Box 1, Folder 40)
  - Condolences, 1922, 1924; (4 folders) (Box 1, Folder 41-44)
  - Cooper Hewitt Museum of Design, 1969-1970 (Box 1, Folder 45)
  - Detroit Institute of Art, 1953-1986 (Box 1, Folder 46)
  - Gallaher, E. B., 1924-1926, undated (Box 1, Folder 47)
  - George F. Harding Museum, 1967-1982 (Box 1, Folder 48)
  - Gorham Company, 1916-1926 (Box 1, Folder 49)
  - Grand Central Art Galleries, 1925-1929 (Box 1, Folder 50)
  - Hall, Wood, and Pound, 1908-1909 (Box 1, Folder 51)
  - Hugenot-Thomas Paine Historical Association, 1974-1979 (Box 1, Folder 52)
  - Ingersoll, Raymond V., circa 1919, 1925-1926 (Box 1, Folder 53)
  - Joslyn Art Museum, 1958-1976 (Box 1, Folder 54)
  - Knapp, Lamont P., 1950-1960, undated (Box 1, Folder 55)
  - Library of Congress, 1906, 1924, 1956, 1987 (Box 1, Folder 56)
  - Logan, Robert Fulton, 1920-1921 (Box 1, Folder 57)
  - Massachusetts Monumental Company, 1909-1910 (Box 1, Folder 58)
  - Milch Galleries, 1920-1927 (Box 1, Folder 59)
  - National Collection of Fine Arts, Smithsonian Institution, 1968-1973; (2 folders) (Box 1, Folder 60-61)
  - Nebraska State Historical Society, 1965-1975 (Box 1, Folder 62)
  - Perham, Douglas and Constance, 1959-1969 (Box 1, Folder 63)
  - Randolph-Macon Women's College, 1965 (Box 1, Folder 64)
  - Requests for Copies of Sound Construction, 1924-1926; (2 folders) (Box 1, Folder 65-66)
  - Roman Bronze Works, 1907-1931 (Box 1, Folder 67)
  - School of American Sculpture, 1920-1925 (Box 1, Folder 68)
  - Saint-Gaudens, Augustus, 1904 (Box 1, Folder 69)
  - Saint Mark's In-The-Bouwerie (Dr. William Norman Guthrie), 1917-1925, 1978 (Box 1, Folder 70)
  - Solon Borglum Memorial Fund, 1922-1924 (Box 1, Folder 71)
  - Tiffany and Co., 1911, 1925-1928 (Box 1, Folder 72)
  - Vogel, Emily (Mimi), 1964-1966 (Box 1, Folder 73)
  - Wallace, Jane, 1921 (Box 1, Folder 74)
  - General Correspondence, 1871-1908; (2 folders) (Box 1, Folder 75-76)
  - General Correspondence, 1909-1989, undated; (13 folders) (Box 2, Folder 1-13)
  - Calling Cards and Business Cards, undated; (Not scanned) (Box 2, Folder 14)
  - Envelopes, 1888, 1903-1966, undated (Box 2, Folder 15)
  - Loose Drafts of Outgoing Correspondence, undated; (2 folders) (Box 2, Folder 16-17)
  - Notepads of Drafts of Outgoing Correspondence, 1905-1910, undated; (7 folders) (Box 2, Folder 18-24)
- Writings and Notes, 1871-1983, undated; Series 4; (Box 2-3; 1.0 linear foot)
  Writings and notes include those written by Solon Borglum and others. Writings and notes by Solon Borglum include project proposals for an Alexander Hamilton statue, the "Bells of History" project, and a sculpture only described as "The Grille." Also found are numerous essays by Solon and lecture notes on topics such as art, material and form, specific sculptural works, and his experiences in World War I. This series also includes Solon's notes on various subjects, including the founding of the School of American Sculpture and the Benjamin Franklin Monument project, and a diary with many sketches that Solon kept in 1918 during his military service. Similarly, Solon wrote in many notebooks during his time in the military and later career. The notebooks found here include personal thoughts, quotations, names and addresses, and sketches. Researchers will also find personal notes written in Solon's address books.
  Writings and notes by others include Emma Borglum's recollections on the life of Solon and their experiences together at the Crow Creek Reservation. Additional recollections on Solon Borglum are written by his daughter Monica Davies and her friend Josephine Sofio. Also found in this subseries is a lecture on Jacob Leisler, the subject of a Borglum sculpture, prepared by Monica's husband, A. Mervyn Davies, and a notebook kept by Emma's brother, Paul Vignal. Of interest are address lists and guest books for the various meetings of the Silvermine Group of Artists. Items in this subseries have not been digitized.
  Arrangement note
  The Writings and Notes series is arranged into 2 subseries:
  4.1: Writings and Notes by Solon Borglum, 1914-1922, undated
  4.2: Writings and Notes by Others, 1871-1983, undated
  - Writings and Notes by Solon Borglum, 1914-1922, undated; 4.1
    - Diary, 1917-1918 (Box 2, Folder 25)
    - Loose Items From Diary, 1918-1919 (Box 2, Folder 26)
    - Project Proposal, "Alexander Hamilton" sculpture, undated; (Partially scanned) (Box 2, Folder 27)
    - Project Proposal, "Bells of History", Tentative Plan, circa 1921; (2 folders; partially scanned) (Box 2, Folder 28-29)
    - Project Proposal, "Bells of History", Drafts and Notes, 1921; (3 folders; partially scanned) (Box 2, Folder 30-32)
    - Project Proposal, "The Grille", 1914 (Box 2, Folder 33)
    - Essay, "The Duty of Art", undated; (Partially scanned) (Box 2, Folder 34)
    - Essay, "The Duty of Art", Notes, undated; (Not scanned) (Box 2, Folder 35)
    - Essay, "The Last Round-up", undated (Box 2, Folder 36)
    - Essay, "The Little Lady of the Dew", circa 1920; (Partially scanned) (Box 2, Folder 37)
    - Essay, "My Experience in the Great War", 1919 (Box 2, Folder 38)
    - Essay, "The Province of a Sculptor", undated (Box 2, Folder 39)
    - Essay, "Reconstruction", undated (Box 2, Folder 40)
    - Lecture, Action and Speech, undated; (Partially scanned) (Box 2, Folder 41)
    - Lecture, Appreciation and Style, undated; (Partially scanned) (Box 2, Folder 42)
    - Lecture, Industrial Arts, undated; (Partially scanned) (Box 2, Folder 43)
    - Lecture, "Inspiration and Aspiration", circa 1920; (2 folders; partially scanned) (Box 2, Folder 44-45)
    - Lecture, Late Nineteenth-century French Artists, undated (Box 2, Folder 46)
    - Lecture, "Presentation", undated (Box 2, Folder 47)
    - Notebooks, 1917-1922, undated; (9 folders) (Box 2, Folder 48-56)
    - Notebooks, undated (Box 3, Folder 1)
    - Notes, Benjamin Franklin Monument, undated (Box 3, Folder 2)
    - Notes, New Canaan, undated (Box 3, Folder 3)
    - Notes, School of American Sculpture, circa 1919-1921; (2 folders; partially scanned) (Box 3, Folder 4-5)
    - Notes, Silvermine Neighbors Club, undated; (Partially scanned) (Box 3, Folder 6)
    - Notes, Miscellaneous, undated; (2 folders; not scanned) (Box 3, Folder 7-8)
    - Address Books, circa 1917-1918, undated; (6 folders) (Box 3, Folder 9-14)
    - Address Lists, undated (Box 3, Folder 15)
  - Writings and Notes by Others, 1871-1983, undated; 4.2; (Not scanned)
    - Emma Borglum, "An Account of the Life of Solon Borglum and the Experience at Crow Creek", undated (Box 3, Folder 16)
    - Emma Borglum, "An Account of the Life of Solon H. Borglum", undated (Box 3, Folder 17)
    - Emma Borglum, Essay on French Literature, undated (Box 3, Folder 18)
    - Emma Borglum, Recipe Notes, undated (Box 3, Folder 19)
    - Emma Borglum, Recollections of Crow Creek, undated (Box 3, Folder 20)
    - Emma Borglum, Recollections of Crow Creek (in French), undated (Box 3, Folder 21)
    - A. Mervyn Davies, Lecture on Jacob Leisler, undated (Box 3, Folder 22)
    - Monica Borglum Davies, "The Command of Got to Retreat", undated (Box 3, Folder 23)
    - Monica Borglum Davies, Recollections of Solon Borglum, 1967, undated (Box 3, Folder 24)
    - Josephine Sofio, Recollections of the Borglum Family, 1979, 1983 (Box 3, Folder 25)
    - Paul E. Vignal, Notebook of Quotations, 1871-1901 (Box 3, Folder 26)
    - Address List, Metropolitan Museum of Art, 1922 (Box 3, Folder 27)
    - Address Lists, Miscellaneous, 1923, undated (Box 3, Folder 28)
    - Guest Books, Silvermine Group of Artists Meetings, circa 1910-1921, (2 folders) (Box 3, Folder 29-30)
    - Miscellaneous Writings, 1925, undated (Box 3, Folder 31)
- Solon Borglum Biography, 1870-1975, undated; Series 5; (Box 3-8; 5.3 linear feet; Not Scanned)